Guide to the West Indian Carnival Documentation Project records 2010.019
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 1: Oral Histories, 28 Gigabytes in 288 files
  - Byron, Cheryl, 1994 September 29; 2010.019.07
    In the interview, Cheryl Byron recalls her early participation playing mas in Carnival in Trinidad and, since the 1970s, as a dancer and poet, in the Brooklyn parade. She describes developing ideas and concepts for her old mas band and what Carnival represents to her personally. Much of the interview focuses on a discussion of the intricacy and ritualism involved in preparations for the parade and the history of the satirical genre of old mas/J'ouvert. She describes some of the positive and negative aspect of the parade; including the greater ethnic inclusion and the growing participation of children, the poor organization, random violence, and the decreased presence of live music. She suggests means of improvement. Noting common misconceptions, surrounding Carnival, Byron suggests community education as a possible solution. She ends by noting the possibilities of garnering greater government support and calls for a tighter network among the diasporic Caribbean Carnivals. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); London (England); Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Toronto (Ont.); Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Trinidadians |x Ethnic identity; Trinidadians |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Byron, Cheryl; Lezama, Carlos; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Cadogan, Glenda, 1995 March 10; 2010.019.08
    Glenda Cadogan was born in Trinidad, became a journalist and came to New York in 1988. She continued as a journalist in New York with the City Sun. She has been very active in Carnival; both Brooklyn and Trinidad. She cofounded a production company, Sapodilla Sisters, that staged plays in Brooklyn in 2014 and 2015. As of 2016, she worked as a media consultant and publicist and held the vice president title at Mauby Media Services.
    In the interview, Glenda Cadogan recalls her first impressions of Brooklyn. She describes herself as a "calypso junkie" and recalls covering the Carnival in Trinidad as a journalist. Cadogan notes some differences between the Brooklyn and Trinidad Carnivals; including organization and differences in levels of participation. She describes her personal connection to Carnival and notes the positive messages sent by the parade and its potential as political catalyst. Cadogan suggests methods of raising awareness about the parade outside the community, distinguishes between the concepts of "parade" and "Carnival," and calls for more mainstream marketing and advertising outside the community. She describes the recent tensions between the Hasidim and Caribbean communities and her modest hopes for bridge-building. She notes recent changes in Brooklyn's Carnival and the connection between local economics and Carnival participation. She is hopeful about the Kiddies Carnival. Cadogan lists her favorite aspects of Carnival and her perceived negative aspects. Cadogan closes by both recognizing the achievements of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA) and calling for innovation within its ranks by way of an infusion of younger blood. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Calypso (Music) |z New York (State) |z New York; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Trinidad; Cadogan, Glenda; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Clavery, Francis "Jackie", 1994 August 18; 2010.019.09
    Francis "Jackie" Clavery was born in Trinidad in 1928 and came to New York in 1966 and to Brooklyn in 1977. He designed and created costumes in conjunction with Randy Brewster, as part of The Culture of Black Creation. He was one of only four designers in Trinidad who worked with copper in Carnival designs.
    In the interview, Clavery recalls getting involved with designing costumes for the Brooklyn parade in conjunction with Randy Brewster. He describes the research process involved in realizing a band's theme. He discusses the deficiencies in New York's judging process and the higher level of competition standard in Trinidad. Clavery describes and demonstrates the process of copper engraving, a rarified technique that he incorporates into his costumes. He explains the need to stay in touch with Trinidad's Carnival in order to keep an edge and stay innovative. Clavery then discusses his personal connection to Carnival. He traces the history of Carnival and describes Trinidad as a unique Caribbean multi-racial melting pot exhibiting more racial harmony than the United States. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Caribbean Americans; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Costume designers; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race relations |z United States; Racism; Trinidad; Clavery, Francis "Jackie"; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Cowie, Jamilla and Sylvia, 1994 August 4; 2010.019.10
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cowie, Jamilla; Cowie, Sylvia; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - DaSilva, Dwight, 1994 July 29; 2010.019.11
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); DaSilva, Dwight; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Davis, Kelvin "Fuzzy", 1994 September 7; 2010.019.12
    Kelvin "Fuzzy" Davis was born in Port of Spain, Trinidad in 1945. He immigrated to Connecticut in 1968, then Brooklyn in 1980 where he is employed by the City of New York as a director in charge of emergency repairs. Davis is an influential costume designer and builder for Brooklyn's Carnival, and involved in the founding of the large costume bands, Borokeet and Midas International. At the 2008 Carnival, he participated with the band Pieces of a Dream. In 2010, he was recorded as a panelist and interviewed as an artist for the Black Brooklyn Renaissance Digital Archive.
    In the interview, Davis describes the theme of his band (Borokeet) and assesses the parade, or Carnival, in Brooklyn. He describes the serious negative effects of policing and the conflict with the Hasidim on the most recent parade of 1994. Davis makes an appeal for the Caribbean community to coalesce and seize political power, especially in light of the economic benefits to the borough. He recounts the history of his involvement with Carnival and his personal connection and training with high profile designers and organizers. He describes collaborative efforts of modern designers and the process of a band realizing the production of its theme. He describes his commitment and love for Carnival and some of the logistics and costs involved. Davis describes changes in Carnival and the commercialization of Trinidad's Carnival. He appeals for greater future collaboration between bands and the West Indian American Day Carnival Association. Davis compares Brooklyn's Carnival with others and regrets its lack of recognition. He ends with a call for national acceptance of the Brooklyn Carnival. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Costume designers |z Trinidad; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidad; Davis, Kelvin "Fuzzy"; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Davis, Paula, 1994 September 19; 2010.019.34
    Paula Davis was born in Trinidad and came to New York to join family members in 1969. She headed her first Carnival band, the "U.S.S. Maple" in 1980. Soon after, she founded Aquarium Productions, working closely with her boyfriend Clyde Bascombe, the band's designer. The bandleader of Aquarium Mas Band, she was initially one of the few women bandleaders in the community. As of 2016, Aquarium has won at many carnivals for the past thirty-five years; from Children to Adult Band categories. They are recipients of over 140 trophies and certificates from carnivals in New York (Brooklyn and Long Island), New Jersey (Orange and Newark), Baltimore, Philadelphia, and Orlando. Davis attributes the possibility of these accomplishments to being inspired, supported, and culturally invested by Bascombe, sister Louella Davis, brother George Davis and Aquarium's friends and supporters.
    In the interview, Paula Davis talks about the internal competition that exists amongst masquerade bands and some of the challenges of being a woman in a male dominated arena. Davis begins with a brief description of her origin, immigration and formative Carnival band experience. She closes with a critique of the process and bias found in the judges who award prizes for the band competitions. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; West Indian Americans; Davis, Paula; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Dublin, Angela, 1994 December 7; 2010.019.13
    Angela Dublin was born in Curacao. As a child her family immigrated to Trinidad & Tobago. In Trinidad, she participated in the Carnival for two years as a child. In 1967, Dublin immigrated to the United States, settling in Brooklyn, New York. She was a participant of the Brooklyn West Indian American Day Carnival. At the time of the interview in 1994, she had not attended Carnival for a number of years, because of a fear of violence.
    In this interview Angela Dublin describes her immigration to the United States. She reflects on the West Indian community's interaction in the seventies. Dublin describes her childhood experiences of Carnival in Trinidad, comparing the historical premise of the event to her personal experience. She also provides detailed histories of the Carnival traditions of Dimanche Gras, calypso and pan music. Dublin discusses the event of the Carnival in 1994, noting the participation of international bands and media. She relates her frustration that although the Carnival produces revenue for the city, it continues to receive little local media coverage. There is also a discussion of a conflict with the Hasidic Jewish community and their desire to reschedule the Carnival because of the Jewish New Year. Dublin notes the influence technology has had on Carnival. She sees Carnival as an art that brings together different communities to share the beauty of the Caribbean culture. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Ethnic identity; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Costume designers |z Trinidad; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidad; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Trinidadians |x Ethnic identity; Dublin, Angela; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Evelyn, Terry, 1994 October 19; 2010.019.14
    Terry Evelyn, born in 1936, was the designer for the Brooklyn Carnival band, Hawks International. A native of Trinidad, he has been in the United States since 1964. Recognized as a prodigy in art and mathematics, his architectural/design career began by designing steel pans. As a child, he found that Carnival in Trinidad was his opportunity to practice and display his artistic skills. His career has been spent as an architect and carnival designer. Evelyn's first job in the States was with Standard Oil. As late as 2010, he remained a vocal proponent of Carnival as a meaningful cultural event for Brooklyn.
    In the interview, Terry Evelyn speaks very strongly about issues of culture, Carnival, race and ethnicity. He begins by remembering his own personal origin weaved in with his early participation in Trinidad's Carnival. Evelyn compares his experience with the judging process for that event with the process in Brooklyn's Carnival. He discusses mounting a presentation for Nelson Mandela's visit to the United Nations that couldn't be executed. He recalls his early participation and the stakeholders involved with Brooklyn's early Carnivals. In 1994, Evelyn was in high demand for his designs and consulting work in several North American Carnivals and he relates details about that. He bemoans that Carnival could be turned into a parade of nudity. Evelyn discusses his architectural design for a proposed performance space in Trinidad. His culturally diverse approach to that is contextualized with the diversity of Brooklyn Carnival. He digresses several times in the last half-hour; taking on several weighty issues, revealing some intolerance and theorizing on conspiracies relating to Jewish influence, war, liberty, and the oppression of African Americans and Caribbean Americans. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Antisemitism; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Costume designers; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations |z United States; Racism; Trinidad; Evelyn, Terry; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Gilbert, Elimus, 1995 February 15; 2010.019.15
    Elimus "Inspector" Gilbert is a Grenadian and was in his mid-twenties at the time of this 1995 interview. Participating as a performer in Carnival since 1985, he had won the Calypso King competition in Grenada on two occasions and was the 1995 Road March King. He was one well-known talent among young Carnival performers and records and performs on the international scene in the decades since. In 2015, he celebrated a thirtieth anniversary in the entertainment business by hosting a multi-act concert, planning a television special and releasing a commemorative and retrospective compilation on compact disc.
    In the interview, Elimus Gilbert thinks that spectator interest in the Labor Day Carnival parade in Brooklyn is dwindling because of the potential for violence. He believes that the West Indian American Day Carnival Association has done a decent job but that there are areas which need improvement. Gilbert would like to see the spectators refrain from joining mas bands before they reach the reviewing stands. "Inspector," as he is known in the calypso world, thinks that it is a great thing for other non-West Indian peoples to get involved in the Carnival. He observes that the event has been underexposed in the mainstream media and he wants that changed. Interview conducted by Michael Roberts.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Canada; Caribbean Americans; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Music; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Grenada; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z New York; Parades |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Gilbert, Elimus; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Lezama, Carlos, 1994 October 19; 2010.019.16
    Carlos Lezama was born on September 3, 1923 in Coro, Venezuela. He grew up in Trinidad but later returned to Venezuela, where he was an auto-worker for General Motors and Chrysler, as well as a mechanic in Caracas specializing in dental machinery. After that, he departed for a job as a merchant mariner. It was during his travels as a seaman that he first visited the United States and eventually resolved to move to New York City, which he did—alone—in 1954. He lived in Manhattan first before moving to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. At some point, his wife and children joined him; they were all congregants at Saint Gregory Catholic Church. He continued to work as a mechanic, taking vocational courses to supplement his training, and after a while was able to buy a home on St. John's Place. During this time, he became a prominent figure in the cultural life of Crown Heights' West Indian residents. Along with Rufus (Lionel) Gorin, he was a key organizer of the first Carnival on Labor Day that went down Eastern Parkway, now commonly called the West Indian Day Parade, in 1969. When Gorin died, Lezama was elected the first president of the West Indian American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA)—a position to which he was repeatedly reelected until he retired in 2002. He died in 2007.
    Lezama, who in 1994 was in his twenty-eighth year as president of the West Indian-American Day Carnival Association (WIADCA), recounts the history of the Carnival and his personal involvement with it. He explains the relocation of the Carnival from Harlem to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and its transformation from a small affair, held mostly indoors in the middle of winter, to a late-summer street festival attracting millions of spectators and participants. He compares the Brooklyn Carnival with its analogues throughout the Caribbean and the United States, especially Trinidad. He describes WIADCA's relationship with city government and the police; both in the aftermath of the 1991 Crown Heights unrest and more recently amid an NYPD "crackdown" on "quality of life" offenses that has affected Carnival participation. He dwells on a dispute with the Hasidim of Crown Heights over the date of the 1994 Carnival, which Lubavitcher Jews claimed would conflict with the holiday of Rosh Hashanah, and how minority-focused newspapers have commented on it. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z United States; West Indian Americans; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Lezama, Carlos; West Indian-American Day Carnival Association; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Millington, Wesley, 1994 September 13; 2010.019.17
    Wesley Millington was born in St. Vincent in 1954. He moved to Brooklyn in 1969 and rarely returns to St. Vincent. He is a founding member of and the designer for Mas Productions; one of the smaller organizations in 1994, with a membership of about fifteen. The group existed in the 1970s under the name of Caribbean Festive Associates but disbanded after a year or two. For the 2015 Carnival, Mas Productions and Millington, in his twenty-third year, were creating costumes at a mas camp in a Brooklyn bakery's basement.
    In the interview, Wesley Millington talks about his design experience and how he wishes to bring more creativity in his designs to Carnival in Brooklyn. He talks about the inner workings of the group, mentioning that one of their goals is to get more women involved in the organization. Millington also mentions the difficulty in getting other Vincentians interested and involved in participating in his organizations. Millington feels that the West Indian American Day Carnival Association could do more to promote and encourage people from other islands to participate in Carnival. Interview conducted by Dwan Reece King.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Carnival; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Saint Vincent and the Grenadines; Trinidad; Millington, Wesley; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Pope, Kelvin, 1995 January 28; 2010.019.18
    Kelvin Pope, also known as "The Mighty Duke," was born in Port Fortin, Trinidad & Tobago to parents from St. Vincent. Pope was an internationally acclaimed calypso singer, winning four consecutive Calypso Monarch awards, a prestigious calypsonian competition. He participated in carnivals around the world, including the West Indian American Day Carnival in Brooklyn, New York. He began participating in the Brooklyn Carnival in 1969. Kelvin Pope died in 2009.